Finding Aid for Squier Family papers, 1843-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Squier Family papers 1843-1977
Squier family.
4 linear feet
85415 Aa2; UAx
Papers of the Squier family of Battle Creek, Michigan. Include letters and diary of John E. Hickman, Civil War soldier in Co. C, 13th Michigan Infantry; letters and miscellanea of Theodore L. Squier, Sr., University of Michigan undergraduate student, medical student and instructor ca. 1914-1921 and Nina La Barge Squier, student in the University of Michigan Nurses' Training Program, 1919-1920; and letters and miscellanea of several family members who served in WWII. Also some records of the American Manufacturing Company of Battle Creek, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Theodore L. Squier, Sr. and family (donor no. 5926 ) in multiple accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
At the center of the Squier Family papers is Theodore L. Squier, Sr., 1919 graduate of the University of Michigan medical school. T. L. Squier, Sr. organized and donated the majority of the collection personally; the numerous annotated envelopes and summary lists found throughout the collection are his work.
T. L. Squier, Sr., was the son of Charles A. Squier and Julia Hickman Squier. His siblings included two sets of twins, Dorothy and Daniel E., and Bernice and Blanche, as well as another brother, John. Daniel E. Squier served in both World Wars, and some of his correspondence from the Second World War is represented in this collection. Bernice and Blanche were co-founders of the Twinzy Toy Company of Battle Creek.
Charles A. Squier co-founded American Manufacturing Company, a tag manufacturer, with his father, Daniel Squier, in Battle Creek in the late 19th century. Daniel Squier of American Manufacturing Company was the fourth in a line of Daniel Squiers; his parents were Daniel Squier (III) and Patience Y. Simpson Squier. The Squier family papers also include a few documents related to the Simpson family.
T. L. Squier, Sr., attended the University of Michigan as an undergraduate student beginning in 1913. In 1919, during his last semester as medical student, he met Nina La Barge, a student in the Nurses' Training Program. Over the next two years, they courted largely through correspondence, as circumstances including an outbreak of influenza in Nina's hometown of Standish, Michigan in early 1920 frequently resulted in their separation. The two were married in Standish on July 1, 1920.
They had three sons: Theodore L. Squier Jr., John D., and Charles L. Theodore and John both served in WWII; their letters from that period are included in the collection. As the other two sons grew up and moved away, Theodore Sr. and Nina frequently wrote letters addressed jointly to Charles and Ted Jr., and later their families. Carbon copies of these letters form the bulk of the collection, and provide a detailed picture of the family's life through the mid-20th century.
The Squier Family Papers are organized into nine series, eight series of documents related to specific members or branches of the family and one series of photographs.
Subjects:
American Manufacturing Company (Battle Creek, Mich.); Battle Creek (Mich.); Business records.; Physicians--Michigan--Battle Creek.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 13th (1861-1865). Company C.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Courtship--Michigan.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Squire family.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Kappa Kappa Fraternity. Alpha Iota Chapter (University of Michigan); Alpha Sigma Phi Fraternity. Theta Chapter (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Fraternities and sororities.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Interiors.; Laboratories.; Phonographs--1911-1920.; Pushball.; Squier, Theodore L.; University of Michigan--Block M--1911-1920.; University of Michigan. Medical School. Class of 1919.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--1911-1920.
Contributors:
Hickman, John E., 1823-1898.; Squier, Theodore L.; Squier, Nina A. La Barge.
Genre Terms:
Daguerreotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Simpson Family
  The Simpson family series includes letters and other materials of Albert B. Simpson and Jeremiah Simpson who served in the Civil War.
  - Albert B. Simpson Correspondence 1860-1863 (Box 1)
    (Civil War letters have been transcribed)
  - Jeremiah Simpson letter re: army service 1863 (Box 1)
- Hickman Family
  The Hickman family series includes letters and a diary of John E. Hickman, Civil War soldier in Co. C, 13th Michigan Infantry.
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellanea 1902-1946 (Box 1)
  - John Hickman
    - Diary, 1861-1864 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1864-1939, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous documents (Box 1)
- Daniel Squier
  The third series, Daniel Squier, contains documents of two 19th-century men, father and son, who were both named Daniel Squier. The elder Daniel Squier was born in 1784 in Halifax, Vermont and lived in Kingston, Wisconsin. His son, Daniel Squier, was born in Salem, New York in 1818. Of particular interest in this series are records of the American Manufacturing Company of Battle Creek, Michigan, which the younger Daniel Squier founded with his son, Charles A. Squier.
  - Business correspondence 1860-1866 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous documents 1890-1892 (Box 1)
  - American Manufacturing Company 1812-1895 (Box 1)
    (War of 1812 supply certificate, inventories, reports, shipping tag examples, tag machine documents, etc.)
  - Minute Book of American Manufacturing Company 1887-1898 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea 1864-1892 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents 1843-1879 (Box 1)
    (Mortgages, patent agreements, letters of agreements, etc.)
- Theodore L. Squier, Sr.
  The fourth series, Theodore L. Squier, Sr., is the largest series in the collection. This series is notable primarily for the information it contains about T. L. Squier, Sr.'s experiences as an undergraduate student, medical student, and instructor at the University of Michigan from 1913-1919. Also contained in this series are a yearbook and scrapbook from Battle Creek High School, both ca. 1912. The bulk of this series consists of carbon copies of correspondence sent throughout the mid-20th century to his sons, on behalf of himself and his wife, Nina A. La Barge Squier.
  - Miscellaneous letters of commendation, appointments, etc., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek High School yearbook "The Palan" 1912 (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek High School scrapbook circa 1912 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - University Musical Society programs and clippings 1916-1919 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan fraternal programs 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Marriage certificate 1920 (Box 1)
  - Travel documents 1928-1951 (Box 1)
  - Journal 1935-1941 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellanea 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - September 1913-February 1918 (Box 1)
    - May-July 1919 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1919, December 1919 (Box 1)
    - February 1920 (Box 1)
    - June 1920 (Box 2)
    - Letter from Charles A. Squier 1925 (Box 2)
    - Travel journal and correspondence 1928-1951 (Box 2)
    - Journal and correspondence
      - 1929-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 2)
      - 1948 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1957-1976 (Box 2)
      (each year has a separate folder)
    - Correspondence to Charles L. Squier
      - 1959-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1977 (Box 2)
- Nina A. La Barge Squier
  The fifth series, Nina A. La Barge Squier, comprises primarily correspondence that she wrote while being courted by Theodore L. Squier between 1919 and 1921. The correspondence is of potential interest to researchers for several reasons. The correspondence from Fall 1919 was written while the future Mrs. Squier was a student in the University of Michigan's Nurses' Training Program. As her suitor, Mr. Squier, was a former member of the student body and faculty at the medical school, he was quite familiar with the hospital where Miss La Barge worked, and so her correspondence to him frequently includes details about her daily life as a student in this program. The other period of potential interest in this body of correspondence is from February 1920, when Miss La Barge returned to her hometown of Standish, Michigan to provide nursing services to her family and others during an influenza outbreak. Again, as her suitor was a medical professional, she frequently included medical details about the outbreak, such as who was ill and what kind of symptoms they were suffering. Finally, this series contains an interesting manuscript account of Nina and Theodore Squier's audience with Pope Pious XII in 1951.
  - Biographical (Box 3)
  - Manuscript, "The La Barge Family Story as told by Joseph La Barge to his Daughter Nina Amelie La Barge and recorded by her" (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
  - Standish High School diploma 1916 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript, "Our Audience with His Holiness, Pius XII" 1951 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1905, 1919, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - February 1920 (Box 3)
    - June 1920 (Box 3)
    - March 1921 (Box 3)
    - Travel Correspondence 1928 (Box 3)
    - 1950-1971 (Box 3)
    - La Barge family correspondence 1931-1942 (Box 3)
    - 1943-1958, 1966, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Addresses to the Girl Scouts of America 1952-1978 (Box 3)
  - WWII Ration Book (Box 3)
- Theodore L. Squier, Jr.
  - Biography and image (Box 3)
  - Baby Book 1921 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1937, 1942-1943 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Key Note Addresses 1944, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1949-1973 (Box 3)
- Daniel E. Squier
  - Correspondence and WWII ephemera 1942-1944 (Box 3)
- John Squier
  - Correspondence from T. L. Squier, Sr. and Nina L. Squier 1936 (Box 3)
  - WWII Military Service (Box 3)
- Charles L. Squier
  - Letters from Summer Camp 1940-1946 (Box 3)
  - Report cards and summer correspondence 1945-1949 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965 (Box 3)
    - 1966 (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
- Other Squier Family Members and Friends
  - Genealogical Research and Family History, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (notes family back to 1639)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Banes, Rachel 1844 (Box 4)
    - Squier, Helen 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    - Whitman, Faith (LaBarge) 1972-1978 (Box 4)
    - Misc. Correspondence 1940-1945 (Box 4)
    - Misc. Correspondence 1952-1978 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The final series in this collection, Photographs, comprises primarily of photographs from the period of Theodore L. Squier, Sr.'s studies at the University of Michigan, ca. 1913-1919. It also contains a miscellaneous assortment of images of members of the Squier family throughout the 19th and 20th centuries.
  - Hickman Family Portraits (Box 4)
  - Squier Family Cabinet Portraits, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Squier Family, Cabinet Sized (Box 4)
  - Early Squier Family (pre 1932) (Box 4)
  - Squier Family (post 1932) (Box 4)
  - Nina Squier (Box 4)
  - Theodore Squier Sr. (Box 4)
  - Theodore Squier Jr. (Box 4)
  - Travel (Box 4)
  - Alpha Sigma Phi fraternity circa 1913-1919 (Box 4)
  - Alpha Kappa Alpha fraternity circa 1913-1919 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor and University of Michigan views circa 1913-1919 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Students 1913-1919 (Box 4)
  - Medical School and Faculty circa 1919 (Box 4)
  - Daniel Squier IV, daguerreotype (Box UAx)
  - Perkins family portrait, tintype (Box UAx)
  - Estella Perkins and man, tintype (Box UAx)
  - Theodore A. Squier and Dell Purchy, tintype (Box UAx)
  - Henry, Ernest and Frank Hickman, tintype (Box UAx)
  - Wilbur, Wesley, and Isaac Hickman, tintype (Box UAx)
  - Hickman family portraits, 2 glass negatives (Box UAx)